现在我们知道了MAC是什么了
我们继续构建第一类安全的MAC
Now that we know what MACs are, let's go
ahead and build our first secure MACs.
首先我想提醒大家，MAC是一对算法
First I want to remind you that a MAC is a
pair of algorithms. The first is a signing
第一个是签名算法，给定信息和密钥，会产生相应的标签
algorithm that's given a message and a key
will generate a corresponding tag. And the
第二个是验证算法，给定密钥、信息和标签
second is verification algorithms are
given a key, message and a tag while
输出0或1，结果取决于标签是否有效
outputs zero or one depending on whether
the tag is valid or not. And we said that
我们说过MAC是安全的，如果它对选择信息攻击
是不可被存在性伪造的
a MAC is secure if it is existentially
unforgeable under a chosen message attack.
换句话说，攻击者可以实施选择信息攻击
In other words, the attackers allow to
mount a chosen message attack where he can
他提交由他选择的任意信息，并获得相应的标签
submit arbitrary messages of his choice
and obtain the corresponding tags for
然后尽管有能力生成任意的标签
those messages, and then despite the
ability to generate arbitrary tags. The
攻击者也不能产生一个新的信息-标签对
attacker cannot create a new message-tag pair that was not given to him
不是选择信息攻击中所给出的信息-标签对
上一节中我们已经看了这个定义
during the chosen message attack. Okay so
we've already seen this definition in the
现在的问题是我们如何构建MAC？
last segment and now the question is how
do we build secure MACs? So the first
我想给大家看的第一个例子是
证明任何安全的PRF可直接
example I want to give you is basically
showing that any secure PRF directly gives
给我们一个安全的MAC。那我们看怎么来做
us a secure MAC as well. So let's see how
we do it. So suppose we have a pseudo
假设我们有一个伪随机函数PRF，这个PRF
取输入X，输出Y
random function so the pseudo random
function takes and inputs X and outputs in
我们定义如下的MAC，我们为信息M签名
Y. And let's define the following MAC. So
the way we sign a message 'M' is basically
即为计算函数在M处的值。所以信息M的标签
by simply evaluating the function at the
point 'M'. So the tag for the message M is
就是在点M处的函数值，然后我们通过这一对来验证信息
simply the value of the function at the
point M and then the way we verify a
方法就是重新计算在信息M处的函数值
message to that pair is by recomputing the
value of the function at the message M and
检查结果是否等于给我们的标签
如果一样，我们说"是"
checking whether that is equal to the tag
given to us. We say yes if so and we
否则我们拒绝。那么这里有图片描述
reject otherwise. So here you have in
pictures basically that when Alice wants
Alice想给Bob发一条信息，她计算标签
通过计算PRF的值得来
to send a message to Bob, she computes a
tag by the value of PRF and then she
那么她把这个得来的标签附在信息后面
Bob收到了这一对信息
appends this tag to the message, Bob
receives the corresponding tag pair, he
他重新计算函数值，并测试得到的标签
recomputes the value of the function and
tests whether the given tag is actually
是否等于在点M处的函数值
那么我们看一个设计得不好的例子
equal to the value of the function at the
point M. So let's look at a bad example of
那么假设我们有一个伪随机函数
this instruction. And so suppose that we
have a pseudo-random function that happens
只输出10位，好，这是一个很好的伪随机函数
to output only ten bits. Okay, so this is
a fine pseudo-random function and it just
对于任何信息M，它只输出10位
so happens that for any message 'M' it
only outputs ten bits value. My question
我的问题是，如果我们使用这个函数F构建了一个MAC
to you is if we use this function 'F' to
construct a MAC, is that going to be a
得到的MAC是安全的吗？那么答案是否定的
这个MAC是不安全的。特别地
secure MAC? So the answer is no, this MAC
is insecure. In particular because the
是因为标签太短。那么考虑下面这个简单例子
tags are too short. So consider the
following simple adversary. What the
攻击者选择一个任意信息M
adversary will do is simply choose an
arbitrary message M and just guess the
随便猜一个MAC的值，作为这个信息的标签
由于这个标签只有10位
value of the MAC for that particular
message. Now, because the tag is only ten
攻击者有1除以2的10次方的机会猜中MAC
bits long, the adversary has a chance of
one in two to the ten in guessing the MAC
换句话说，攻击者猜测的优势
correctly. In other words, the advantage
of the guessing adversary, one distinctly
给定信息，猜测不同的随机标签
攻击者将有一个
guesses a random tag for a given message.
That adversary is going to have an
对这个MAC的优势就是1除以2的10次方
advantage against the MAC that's basically
one over two to the ten which is one over
即1024分之一，当然不是可忽略的
a thousand twenty four and that's
definitely non negligible. So the adversary
那么攻击者会成功地为给定的信息伪造MAC
basically will successfully forge the MAC
on a given message with probability one
以千分之一的概率，这是不安全的
但事实上这是唯一的会有错误的例子
on a thousand which is insecure. However
it turns out this is the only example that
仅当函数输出太小，事情才会有问题
where things can go wrong, only when the
output of the function is small can things
如果这个PRF的输出很大，我们就可以获得一个
这个函数的安全的MAC
go wrong. If the output of the PRF is
large, then we get a secure MAC out of this
我们看一个安全性定理。假设我们有
function. And let's state the security
theorem here. So suppose we have a
一个函数F，取X中的信息为输入，输出Y中的标签
function 'F' that takes messages in 'X'
and outputs tags in 'Y', then the MAC
那么由这个PRF推出的MAC事实上是安全的。特别地
that's derived from this PRF in fact is a
secure MAC. In particular, if you look at
如果大家看这个安全性定理，会很清楚地看到
这个误差上界，换句话说
the security theorem here, you'll see very
clearly the error bounds, in other words
由于PRF是安全的，我们知道这个量是可忽略的
since the PRF is secure we know that this
quantity here is negligible. And so if we
如果我们希望这个量是可忽略的
这是我们想要的，我们想说
want this quantity to be negligible, this
is what we want, we want to say that no
没有攻击者可以击败MAC I_F，意味着
我们希望这个量是可忽略的
adversary can defeat the MAC 'I sub F',
that implies that we want this quantity to
换句话说，我们希望输出空间很大
be negligible, in other words we want the
output space to be large. And so for
例如，取一个PRF，输出80位就很好了
example, taking a PRF that outputs eighty
bits is perfectly fine. That will generate
它们会产生80位MAC，因此任意攻击者的优势
an eighty bit MAC and therefore the
advantage of any adversary will be at most
最多是1除以2的80次方。那么这个定理的证明很简单
one over two to the eighty. So now the proof
of this theorem is really simple, so let's
我们来看看，事实上我们不从PRF开始
just go ahead and do it. So in fact let's
start by saying that suppose instead of a
假设我们有一个从信息空间到标签空间的真随机函数
PRF we have a truly random function from
the message space to the tag space so this
这是一个从X到Y的真随机函数
它是从所有函数集中随机选择的
is just a random function from X to Y
that's chosen at random from the set of
我们看这个函数能否给我们一个安全的MAC
all such functions. Now let's see if that
function can give us a secure MAC. So what
那么攻击者说，我想要信息M1的标签
the adversary says is, 'I want a tag on
the message M1'. What he gets back is the
他获得了标签，即在点M1处的函数值
tag which just happens to be the function
evaluated at the point M1. Notice there is
注意这里没有密钥，因为F只是一个从X到Y的真随机函数
no key here because F is just a truly
random function from X to Y. And then the
然后攻击者从选择信息M2，他获得了M2的标签
adversary gets to choose a message from M2
and he obtains the tag from M2, he chooses
他选择M3,M4直到Mq，他获得了所有对应的标签
M3, M4 up to MQ and he obtains all the
corresponding tags. Now his goal is to
现在他的目标是产生一个信息标签对
也就说他赢了，记得那就是
produce a message tag pair and we say that
he wins, remember that this is an
存在性伪造，换句话说，首先一定有T=F(M)
existential forgery, in other words first
of all T has to be equal to F of M. This
这意味着T是M的一个有效标签。其次
means that 'T' is a valid tag for the
message 'M'. And second of all, the
信息M必须是新的，信息M不能是M1到Mq中的任何一个
message 'M' has to be new. So the message
'M' had better not be one of M-one to M-Q.
那我们想一想这是什么意思
But let's just think about this for a
minute, what does this mean? So the
攻击者看到在点M1到Mq处这个真随机函数的值
adversary got to see the value of a truly
random function at the points M-one to M-Q
现在他要预测新点M的函数值
and now he's suppose to predict the value
of this function as some new point, M
但是对于真随机函数，在点M的函数值
However, for a truly random function, the
value of the function at the point M is
与在点M1到Mq处的值是独立的，所以攻击者能做的
independent of its value at the points M-1
to M-Q. So the best the adversary can do
最好的预测点M的函数值，就是猜
at predicting the value of the function at
the point M is just guess the value,
因为他没有任何函数F在M处的值的信息
因此他的优势
because he has no information about F of
M. And as a result his advantage if he
如果他猜在点M处的函数值，他猜中的概率
guesses the value of the function at the
point M he'll guess it right with
是1除以|Y|。然后他产生的标签以概率1除以|Y|
probability exactly one over Y. And then
the tag that he produced will be correct
是正确的。好，攻击者没有任何信息
with probability exactly one over Y. Okay,
again he had no information about the
是关于函数在M的值，最好的办法就是猜
value of the function of M and so the best
he could do is guess. And if he guesses,
猜的话，他以1除以|Y|的概率猜对。当然
he'll get it right with probability one
over Y. And now of course, because the
因为函数F是伪随机函数，当我们
function capital F is a pseudo random
function, the adversary is gonna behave the
给攻击者真随机函数或伪随机函数
攻击者表现是一样的
same whether we give him the truly random
function or the pseudo random function.
攻击者不能说出它们的区别
因此，即使我们有一个伪随机函数
The adversary can't tell the difference
and as a result even if we use a pseudo
攻击者在游戏中获胜的优势最多为1除以|Y|
random function, the adversary is gonna
have advantages at most one over Y in
好，那么大家可以看到这个安全性定理
winning the game. Okay, so you can see
exactly the security theorem, let's go
我们回头看一会。这是为什么我们有这一误差项
back there for just a second. Essentially
this is basically why we got an error term
1除以|Y|，因为是猜测攻击所致，而且猜测
是攻击者为了赢得游戏
of one over Y because of the guessing
attack and that's the only way that the
唯一能做的。那么现在我们知道任何PRF
attacker can win the game. So now that we
know that any secure PRF is also a secure
同时也是安全的MAC，我们已经知道
我们有了第一种MAC的例子。特别地
MAC, we already know that we have our
first example MAC. In particular, we know
我们知道AES，或者我们至少相信
AES是一个安全的PRF，因此
that AES, or at least we believe that AES
is a secure PRF, therefore, AES since it
由于AES取16字节的输入，AES的信息空间是128位
takes sixteen byte inputs, right the
message space for AES is 128 bits, which
即16字节。因此AES加密会给我们一个MAC
is sixteen bytes. Therefore the AES cipher
essentially gives us a MAC that can match
匹配严格的16字节信息。好的，这是我们的第一个MAC例子
messages that are exactly sixteen bytes.
Okay, so that's our first example of a
现在问题是，如果我们有了一个PRF
针对像AES这样的小输入，仅16字节的
MAC. But now the question is if we have a
PRF for small inputs like AES that only
那么我们能不能为长信息也构建一个MAC呢？
acts on sixteen bytes, can we build a MAC
for big messages that can act on gigabytes
比如几个G的数据呢？有时我把这个称之为麦当劳问题
of data? Sometimes I call this the
McDonald's problem. Basically given a
给一个小的MAC，我们构建它的一个大MAC
换句话说，给定短信息的MAC
small MAC and we build a big MAC out of
it. In other words, given a MAC for small
我们构建长信息的MAC。我们看两个这样的机制
messages and we build a MAC for large
messages. So we're gonna look at two
第一个例子叫做CBC MAC
constructions for doing so. The first
example is called a CBC MAC that again
取针对短信息的PRF为输入
输出一个PRF，可以处理长信息
takes PRF for small messages as input
and produces a PRF for very large
作为输出。第二个我们要看的机制是HMAC
它做到事情是一样的
messages. As outputs. The second one we'll
see is HMAC which does the same thing
取处理短输入的PRF，产生能处理长输入的PRF
again takes a PRF for small inputs and
generates a PRF for very large inputs. Now
现在这两个被用在了不同的上下文中
the two are used in very different
contexts. CBC-MAC is actually very
CBC-MAC在银行业广为应用
例如有一个系统叫做
commonly used in the banking industry. For
example, there's a system called the
自动打扫房间ACH，银行使用这个系统来处理
银行之间的支票
Automatic Clearing House, ACH, which banks
use to clear checks with one another and
CBC-MAC被用来确保支票的完整性
that system, CBC-MAC, is used to ensure
integrity of the checks as they're
支票是在银行之间传递的。在因特网上
SSL、IPsec和SSH等协议
transferred from bank to bank. On the
Internet, protocols like SSL and IPsec and
都使用HMAC来保护完整性。这两个不同的MAC
SSH, those all use HMAC for integrity. Two
different MACs and were gonna discuss them
我们将在下面几节中讨论它们
如我所说，从处理短信息的PRF出发
in the next couple of segments. And as I
said were also gonna start from a PRF for
产生能够处理几个G的信息的PRF
small messages and produce PRF for
messages that are gigabytes long and in
特别地，它们两种MAC都可以用AES作为底层密码
particular they can both be substantiated
with AES as the underlying cipher. So the
那么我最后想说的，关于这些基于PRF的MAC的
last comment I want to make about these
PRF based MACs is that in fact their
事实上它们的输出是可以被截断的
假设我们有一个PRF，输出N位
output can be truncated. So suppose we
have a PRF that outputs N bit outputs. So
对于AES，这是一个输出128位的PRF
again for AES this would be a PRF that
outputs 128 bits as outputs. It's an easy
这是一个容易证明的引理。事实上如果你有一个
N位PRF，如果你截断之，换句话说
lemma to show that in fact if you have an
N bit PRF if you truncated, in other words
如果你值输出前K位，结果依然是安全的PRF
if you only output first K bits, the
result is also a secure PRF and the
直观地说，如果大PRF对任意输入，都能
输出N位随机字符串
intuition here is if the big PRF outputs N
bits of randomness for any inputs that you
那么把结果截断成T位后
give to the PRF then certainly chopping it
off and truncating it to T bits is still
看上去依然是随机的。攻击者获得更少的信息
gonna look random. The attacker now gets
less information so his job of
所以他区分随机输出的工作会更困难。换句话说
distinguishing the outputs from random
just became harder. In other words, if the
如果N位PRF是安全的，那么T(<N)位PRF，截断PRF
N bit PRF is secure, then the T less than
N bit PRF, the truncated PRF, would also
也是安全的。这是一个简单的引理，由于任何安全PRF
be secure. So this is an easy lemma and
since any secure PRF also gives us a
也能给我们一个安全的MAC，这意味着如果你给我
一个基于PRF的MAC
secure MAC, what this means is if you give
me a MAC that's based on a PRF and what I
我可以把它截断成W位，但是，因为
基于PRF的MAC的定理中的误差项
can do is I can truncate it to W bits,
however, because of the error term in the
我们知道截断到W位是安全的
MAC based PRF theorem we know that
truncating to W bits will only be secure
只要1除以2的|W|次方是可忽略的
那么如果你截断PRF到只有3位
as long as one over two to the W is
negligible. So if you truncate the PRF to
那么得到的MAC就不是安全的。不过
only three bits, the resulting MAC is not
going to be secure. However, if you
如果你把它截断成80位，甚至是64位
那么得到的MAC也是
truncate it to say 80 bits or maybe even
64 bits, then the resulting MAC is still
一个安全的MAC。好，需要记住的事情是
gonna be a secure MAC. Okay, so the thing
to remember here is that even though we
即使我们使用AES来构建更大的PRF
最后PRF的输出将是128位
use AES to construct larger PRFs and the
output of these PRFs is gonna be 128 bits,
这并不意味着MAC自身必须产生128位标签
it doesn't mean that the MAC itself has to
produce 128 bit tags. We can always
我们总可以把结果截断成90位或80位
因此，我们依然可以得到
truncate the outputs to 90 bits or 80
bits, and as a result, we would get still
安全的MAC，但现在输出标签有着更合理的大小
secure MACs but now the output tag is
gonna be more reasonable size and doesn't
不必是满满的128位。好，在下一节中
have to be the full 128 bits. Okay, so in
the next segment we're gonna look at how
我们看CBC-MAC的工作
the CBC-MAC works.